<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The answer of the generall assembly in Scotland to the letter of some of their reverend brethren of the ministry in England sent by Mr Marshall and Mr Nye to the said Assembly</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58597</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12090145</idno>
  <idno type="VID">53835</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240937765</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8068</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12090145</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58597)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53835)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 239:E67, no 17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The answer of the generall assembly in Scotland to the letter of some of their reverend brethren of the ministry in England sent by Mr Marshall and Mr Nye to the said Assembly</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Dexter, for Henry Overton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Sept. 16, 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Marshall, Stephen, 1594?-1655.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Westminster Assembly (1643-1652). --  Letter from the Assembly of divines in England, to the General Assembly in Scotland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53835:1"/>
            <p>THE ANSWER <hi>OF THE</hi> Generall Assembly IN SCOTLAND, TO The Letter of some of their Reverend Brethren of the Ministry In <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> Sent by M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Marshall,</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Nye</hi> to the said Assembly.</p>
            <p>Ordered to bee Printed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Dexter,</hi> for <hi>Henry Overton. Anno</hi> 1643. <hi>Sep<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 16.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:53835:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53835:2"/>
            <head>THE ANSVVER OF THE Generall Assembly To the Letter of some of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Brethren of the Ministery in ENGLAND, sent by Mr. <hi>Marshall</hi> and Mr. <hi>Nye,</hi> to the said Assembly.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee acknowledge with thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnesse to God, that this it one of the greatest blessings bestowed upon our Kirke, and a pleasant fruit of our free As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies, that a way is opened for keeping Communion with our Sister Kirks abroad, and correspondence with you our deare Brethren, in whose joy and sorrow we have so neere interest, and whose cause and condition wee desire to lay to heart as our owne.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:53835:3"/>
            <p>All your former Letters were most acceptable and full of refreshment unto us, being taken as the earnest of a more full and constant fellowship lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged after and hoped for. And this your last, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though full of sadnesse and sorrow, yet accompted of us all most wor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy of our tenderest affection and best respects, both for your cause who sent it, and for these worthy witnesses who did attest it: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as you have given unto us no small evidence▪ not onely of your love, but also of trust and friendly respect, by choosing to poure out your grieved soules in our bosome; so wee shall wish and GOD willing endeavour, that you may really find some measure of brotherly compassion in our receiving thereof: For these your sad expressions of deepe sorrow, being (as you give us to conceive) but a part of your complaint, and a lamentation lesse then the cause doth require, cannot but melt every heart, wherein there is any the least warmenesse of the love of Christ and his Saints. And what Child of the Bridegroom-Chamber can heare the voice of so many Friends of the Bridegroom, lamenting for the evills which have befalne Christs Bride in <hi>England,</hi> in the very night before the expected espousals, and not sit downe and mourne with them; except his heart be falne a sleepe and frozen within him. The pitifull condition of your Church in <hi>England,</hi> is matter enough wee confesse to move, yea to rend our bowels.</p>
            <p>If wee should weigh this your heavie griefe in the scales of common reason, wee behoved either to stand aloft from your plangue, as men astonished, or sinke downe in heavinesse, and bee swallowed up of Sorrow: But when wee ponder your sad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the ballance of the sanctuary, wee find that nothing hath as yet befalne unto you, save that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53835:3"/> which hath beene the exercise of the Saints in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mertimes, who have beene made to sit downe for a while in the shadow of death before the day of their deliverance; Wee find nothing but that which may bee a fit preparation for a comfortable out gate from all your troubles. What if it was necessary in the wise dispensation of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty GOD, that a People in great estimation for wisedome and power, such as the <hi>English,</hi> should bee thus farre humbled as you declare, to the end that your deliverance may bee seene hereafter to bee of the Lord, and not of your selves? What if the Lord would not draw back his hand from the wine-presse wherein you now doe lye, untill hee should draw forth from you these pitifull expressions of your low Estate, and so provide for himselfe Witnesses against the day to come, that hee may have the greater and purer glory in your salvations, and your gloriation may bee in the Lord alone?</p>
            <p>Deare Brethren, comfort your selves in the Lord, this sowing in teares doth promise a reaping in joy, and (who knowes how soone) hee will give to you who are mourners in Sion, beauty for ashes, the oyle of gladnesse for mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the garment of praise for the spirit of heavinesse, that you may bee called trees of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse, the planting of the Lord, that hee may be glorified.</p>
            <p>Though weep<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng be in the evening of this begun Reform<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion and purgeing of the Lords House a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you, yet in the morning, when the discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red filthines and sweepings of the Temple shall bee orderly cast out, joy shall come with thanksgiving and praise: Though a fire be kindled in the Land, yet
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53835:4"/> it is not to consume any of the Mettall for the Lord is sitting down as a refiner amongst you, and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to purifie the Sons of <hi>Levy,</hi> that he may have a more pure oblation of spirituall worship and service in all his holy Ordinances throughout all the Land: which is no token of wrath, but of loving kindnes towards you.</p>
            <p>No wonder that <hi>Sathan</hi> doth thus rage as you relate forseeing his casting out: No wonder he stir up all the Children of disobedience, and kindle their naturall malice against the Children of God with the inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of hellish furie: No wonder the spirit of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist be mad, when the morsell, halfe swallowed downe, is like to be pulled out of his throat; The fat morsell of the rich Revenues of <hi>England:</hi> No wonder he be cruel against you the servants of <hi>Christ,</hi> who are consuming him by the breath of the Lords mouth. You doe well to expect no mercie if Papists and Prelates prevaile over you: Neither desire wee to deceive our selves, in hopes to be free from what their power and malice can doe against us: For they will not doe to us, if they get the upper hand, as we have done, and must doe, if God bring them low a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againe under us, as they were before: For wee and they are led by the contrarie Spirits of Christ and Anti-Christ.</p>
            <p>We have laboueed and must labour for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, but they except in so farre as God shall bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle them, will not rest without our destruction. For their furie against our persons is much more fiery then our zeale is fervent against their abominations: Let them follow the Spirit of lying and murthering wee must take us to our refuge, and joine our selves with all that are sensible of the danger of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion, in prayer and supplication, <hi>The Lord
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53835:4"/> of Hosts is with us, the God of Iacob is our refuge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for advice, what can wee say to you, who are upon your watch Tower? where is the spirit of wisedome and counsell? who lye as humble Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples under the Lords feet, that did never forsake them that sought him. Goe on in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, against all opposition without, feare of whatsoever dangers, to purge the house of the Lord, to repair the breaches thereof, to set up all his Ordinances in their full beauty and perfection, to the uttermost of your power, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the patterne of the Word of God, and zeale of the best reformed Kirks, and let these two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes be knit together as one man in maintaining and promoving the truth of the Gospell: Let us e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven enter in a perpetuall Covenant for our selves and posterity, to endeavour that all things may be done in the house of the Lord according to his owne will, and let the Lord doe with us, what seemeth good in his eyes; Onely waite upon the Lord, bee of good courage, and he shall strengthen your heart. Let your hands be ever at your Masters worke, and hold your faces resolutely to his Cause. <hi>Watch yee, stand fast in the faith, quit your selves like men, be strong, for you shall see the Salvation of the Lord, and your labour shall not bee in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Arch. Iohnson, Cler. Eccles.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>